hey folks Brett here this video is a
response to a question submitted by one
of my longest standing patreon
supporters Kevin Fosse it's an excellent
question question is is there a cultural
analog to senescence now senescence is a
term that is probably not terribly
familiar to most of you so I'm going to
explain it a little bit and explain why
it happens biologically and then we can
address Kevin's question so senescence
is what we typically refer to as aging
it is the tendency of creatures to
become less efficient and more
vulnerable with age and it's a very
interesting process it's when I studied
during that in my dissertation work it
happens for a reason we have come to
understand pretty well evolutionarily
the reason is this the genes in our
genome have to do multiple jobs they're
just simply aren't enough of them to do
all of the work necessary to make a
self-assembling 30 trillion cell self
maintaining organism like ourselves we
have something like 20,000 genes in our
protein coding genomes those genes may
have five different edits on average per
gene which gives you something like a
hundred thousand different combinations
that's not nearly enough to deal with
all of the machinery of the 200-plus
cell types that we have in our bodies
and the long developmental program that
puts all of these things in the correct
order so it is necessarily true that
genes will tend to do more than one
thing we call a gene that does more than
one thing pleiotropic it is a playa
trophy and it means a gene that has
multiple functions so the key insight as
to what this has to do with the process
of senescence comes from one of the
great evolutionary biologists of the
20th century guy named George Williams
who I knew before his death George
Williams reck
that pleiotropic effects would very
often pull in different directions and
that for any gene where the benefit came
early in life and the harm came late in
life selection would tend to favor the
team in spite of the harm and the reason
for that is fairly simple the late life
effect of that gene will not be
experienced by nearly as many
individuals as the early life benefit of
the gene because many individuals won't
survive to experience so the later in
life the negative effect happens the
less selection is capable of purging it
from our genomes
this results in genes that have early
life benefits and late life harms
accumulating in our genomes and creates
a tendency for those late life effects
to degrade our function over time
beginning not at Birth but beginning at
the moment of first reproduction for the
species that is the usual moment at
which individuals in that species begin
reproducing so for human beings we don't
measure senescence until an individual
reaches something like 18 or 20 years of
age at which point decline begins to be
measurable and it accelerates through
the lifespan until there's nobody left
so the question is is there a cultural
analog to this process of selection of
senescence that is driven by selection
for early life benefits in spite of late
life costs and unfortunately the answer
is yes and our economic and political
systems are tailor-made to bring it
about I believe we are actually seeing a
kind of senescence unfold right before
our eyes
here's the reason our system has a
fundamentally competitive nature at its
core and ideas that work in the
short-term but fail and cause
vulnerability in the long term
tend to survive in our system because
they tend to produce economic benefits
so if you engage in the production of
some technology that produces benefits
for Humanity over the course of several
decades and then the harm of that
technology manifests over later decades
you will have become wealthy in the
short term that wealth will have
resulted in an increase in your
political influence and therefore it
will reinforce the belief structures
that made it seem like a good idea in
the first place even if they delayed
costs of whatever modality it is that
you introduced into the world far exceed
the benefits that initially came from it
so the simple fact that the market tends
to see those short-term gains and
discount the long-term effects until the
political structure has already been
modified by that success will create a
phenomenon that is not just like
biological senescence but I would argue
is actually the very same process
unfolding now how would that manifest
for us it would manifest in a system
that was incapable of going in Reverse a
system that would drive off the cliff
rather than recognize that something at
its core was awry and leading us into
danger
so that really couldn't be a better
description of where we are we have a
system that makes us very comfortable in
the short term it provides for our needs
and it is liquidating the well-being of
the planet at an incredible rate that
analytically we know full well cannot
continue and yet we do not change course
because of the senescence of
civilization hey folks if you like this
video click like subscribe to the
channel and if you feel like supporting
the creation of more content like this
head on over to my patreon page and sign
up at whatever level feels comfortable